A Guide to the Monticello Music Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part I: Monticello Music Collection, 6 boxes
  - (Box-folder 4:21)
    II Sonates Pour le Clavecin Avec accompagnement d'un Violon ad Libitum. Dediées á Madame Dillon Lee par M. Edelman, Ouevre VII. Inscribed: "Martha Jefferson, Paris 1786." Published Chez auteur, Chez M. D'argenville, rue Dutemple, au coin de celle de Pastourelle, Paris. Price: 4tt. Printed sheet music.
  - Bound volume, with covers missing. (Box-folder 4:22)
    Harpsichord Sonatas by Dibdin. Inscribed: "Mlle. Jefferson L'Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris."
    Sonatines or Easy Lessons for the Harpsichord Calculated for the improvement of young Practitioners on that Instrument by Sig. C. Wagenseil To which are added several favorite Airs and Lessons by Graff, Toeschi, Pescetti, Rutini T. Giordani. The whole intended to form a gradual Series of Practice for Learners. Printed for John Johnston near Exeter Change Strand and Longman Lukey and Co. No. 26 Cheapside. Price: 3s.
    A Favorite Lesson For the Harpsichord, one composed by Mr. Geo Green, the second by Sig. Castrucci. Published [London, ca. 1770-80].
  - Hardbound volume, containing three small volumes of French songs for voice and keyboard accompaniment and texted verses., Inside cover inscribed: "Mlle Jefferson Abbaye Royale du Panthemont Paris." (Box-folder 4:23)
    Includes mainly pastorals, romances, and rondos:
    Recueil de Petits Airs et Pastorales Tirées du Roman D'Estelle avec Accompagnement de Piano-Forte ou Harpe par Mr. Darondeau, Oeuvre VI. Published Chez l'Auteur rue Traversiere á coté de l'Hotel d'Autriche No. 24, Paris [ca. 1785]. Price: 6tt.
    Recueil de Romances et D'Ariettes avec Accompagnement de Clavecin ou de Piano-Forte Dedié á son Altesse Madame la Princesse Caroline de Nassau Usingen par Mr. Darondeau, Oeuvre IV. Published Chez Lauteur Rue des Mouline Butte St. Roch No. 9 Paris [ca. 1785]. Price: 7tt.
  - Large bound volume of solo keyboard music with MISS JEFFERSON stamped in gold on the cover., Inscribed: "Mlle. Martha Jefferson Abbaye Royale de Panthemont, Paris 1785." Inside blank page inscribed with "Melle. Jefferson" in pencil above a faded quote in red. (Box-folder 5:24)
    Begins on page 5 of Mozart's Terzette [Trio] in G-major (indicated at the bottom of page). Followed by title page: Le Tout Ensemble, de Musique, pour le Forte Piano, ou Clavecin avec Accompagnements par les grands Maitres de L'Europe et trés humblement dedié aux premiers delitanti de Musique de la Grande Bretagne par l'editeur. Printed and sold by J. Bland at his grand music warehouse, 45 Holborn. [London, ca. 1786]. The violin and cello parts follow this title page.
    Several pages of untitled manuscript music, inscribed "Maria Jefferson" at the beginning. [There is a handwritten card tucked inside the manuscript that reads: These pages are copies (by Maria Jefferson?) of Nicolai's op. 3 Sonata I and Sonata II. The rondo of 1 was probably completed on a page now cut out and removed from the volume. R. Kidd 6/87].
    Niccolai's Sonata op. 3, nos. III, IV, V, VI, [ca. 1785]. Sonatas for violin and piano.
    Six Sonatas for the Piano Forte or Harpsichord with an accompaniment for a violin composed by J[ohann Franz Xaver] Sterkel. Printed by Longman & Broderip, No. 26 Cheapside & No. 13 Hay Market where may be had all the compositions of this author [London, ca. 1790]. Price: 10.
    Sei Sonate per Cembalo o Pianno Forte con Violinno ad Libitom composte da Matia Vento Gravée par Mme. La V. Leclair. Opus II, Nuovamente Stampata a Spese di G. B. Venir. Chez M. Venier, Editeur de plusieurs Ouvrages de Musique Rue Traversiere vis á vis l'Hotel de Richelieu et aux Adresses Ordinares a Lyon aux addresses de Musique avec privilege du roy [Lyon, ca. 1785]. Prix: 7/4.
    Quatre Sonates pour la Harpe avec Accompagnement de Violon et Basse, ad labium par M. Gros op. III [Paris, ca. 1770].
    Unidentified sonatas IV, V, VI for keyboard duet.
    Six Sonates pour le Clavecin ou Piano-Forte avec Accompagnement de Violon ad Libitum par Valentin Nicolay, op. 11. Chez Leduc successeur de Mr. de la Chevardiere Rue de Foule a la Croix d'Or au Magazin de Musique et d'Instruments [Paris, ca. 1785]. Inscribed: "Miss Jefferson, Paris 1785."
    Concertos of Monsr. Schobert's Works for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte, op. 11-15, nos. Printed by J. Bland No. 45 Holborn of whom may be had in Numbers, all this Composers Sonatas. [London, ca. 1790]. Price: 1$. Concertos Pr: 2$.
    Sigr. [Joseph] Haydn's Grand Orchestra Sinfonie as Performed at the Nobility's Concerts, adapted for the Organ, Harpsichord or Piano Forte. Printed for J. Bland at his Music Warehouse, No. 45 Holborn [London, ca. 1785]. Price: 2. Keyboard adaptation by Mr. Tindal of Haydn's First Symphony in G major.
    The Celebrated Overture 'La Chasse' composed by Sig. Giuseppe Haydn adapted for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte. Printed by Longman and Broderip, No. 26 Cheapside and No. 13 Hay Market [London, ca. 1785].
    A Concerto for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte with Accompaniments for Two Violins, Two Horns, Two German Flutes or Oboes, a Tenor and Violoncello by J. F. Kooffer. Printed for W. Napier Music seller to their Majesties, No. 4, in Strand, [London, ca. 1780]. Concerto No. III.
    A Favorite Concerto for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte, with Accompaniments for two Violins, Hautboys, or Flutes, two Horns ad libitum, Tenor, and Violoncello, Composed by Vincent Manfredini Master and Composer to the Empires of Russia. Printed for and sold by J. Bland No. 45 High Holborn where may be had great variety of New Music by the best Authors [London, n.d.].
    The Celebrated Overture Composed by Sig. Haydn and Performed at Mels Bach and Abel's Concerts adapted for the Piano Forte or Harpsichord. Printed by Longman and Broderip, No. 26 Cheapside and No. 13 Haymarket [London, ca. 1790].
    Three Sonatas for the Harpsichord or Piano Forte Composed by the Celebrated W. A. Mozart of Vienna, Op. 5. Printed by J. Bland at his Music Warehouse, No. 45 Holborn where may by had all the above composer's Works also the greatest variety of Music English & Foreign. NB: This is the Favorite Set Played at the Nobility's Concerts and Anacreontic Society [London, ca. 1786]. Price: 4$.
  - Bound volume, with green cover., Inscribed to: "Mlle. Jefferson Abbaye Royale de Panthemont Paris 1738." Inscribed: "Martha Jefferson, Panthemont" on top of second page. (Box-folder 4:25)
    Sonates in Quatuor pour le Clavecin avec accompagnement de deux violins une basse et deux cors dédiées a Mademoiselle de Lamoignon par Mr. Balbastre organize de Monsieur Frere du Roi de la Metropole de Paris et de L'Eglise Paroissiale de St. Roch. Oeuvre III, [Paris, ca. 1780]. Prix: 12.
    Six Sonates pour le Piano-Forte ou le Clavecin avec accompagnement d'une flutte ou violon compose par. M. Clementi, Oeuvre II. Chez Mr. Bailleux, Md. De Musique ordinaire du Roy et de la famille Royale a la Regle d'Or Rue St. Honore pres celle de la Lingerie.[Paris, ca. 1783]
    Six Sonatas for the Piano Forte or the Harpsichord with an Accompanyment for a Violin or Flute Humbly dedicated to Mr. Phillips composed by Signor Clementi, op. IV. Printed by Longman and Broderip No. 26 Cheapside and No. 13 Haymarket [London, ca. 1783]. Price: 10.6
    La Chasse pour Le Clavecin ou Forte Piano par Leopold Kozeluch, Oeuvre V, [Vienne, ca. 1781]
    IIme Recueil de Petits Airs de Chant avec Accompagnement de Piano-Forte ou de Harpe Dédié á Madame Le Brun de l'Academie Royale de Peinture par M. Martini. Includes: Chanson Parole du Roman de Galathée, Complainte de la Reine Stuard en prison, L'amante irrésolve, Le veritable maitre de Chant, La Veuve inconsolable, Le Berger Infidéle, Le Novice de la Trappe, and L'Epousée de Jour. Published Chez des Lauriers M. de Papiers rue St. Honoré á coté de celle des Prouvaires, Paris [ca. 1770]. Price: 9tt.
  - Bound volume, with green hardcover., Inscribed: Thomas Jefferson "Monticello" Albemarle Country, Virginia on front cover. Inscribed: Thomas Jefferson Monticello on title page. (Box-folder 4:26)
    Sonates pour le Clavecin avec accompagnement du Violon ad libitum dediees a Monsieur Garnier Intereffe dans les affaires du roy par Mr. Schobert, Claveceniste de S. A. S. Monseigneur Le Prince de Conty, Oeuvre. V. Chez M. Bailleux Md. De Musique ordinaire du Royale de la famille Royale et de l'Ecole Royale de Musique [Paris, ca. 1785]. Prix: 4f.
    Sonatas en Quatuor pour le Clavecin avec accompagnement de deux Violon et Basse ad Libitum dediees a Monsieur le Comte de Brancas Ancien Colonel d'Infanterie par Mr. Schobert Claveceniste de S. A. S. Monseigneur Le Prince de Conty, Oeuvre III. Chez M. Bailleux Md. De Musique ordinaire du Royale de la famille Royale et de l'Ecole Royale de Musique [Paris, ca. 1785]. Prix 4f.
    Sinfonies pour le Clavecin avec Accompagnements de Violon, Cors, ad libitum dediees a Melle du Chaffou par Mr. Schobert Claveceniste de S. A. S. Monseigneur le Prince de Conty, Op. IX. Chez M. Bailleux Md. De Musique ordinaire du Royale de la famille Royale et de l'Ecole Royale de Musique ... Schobert [Pars, ca. 1785]. Prix: 4f.
    Sinfonies pour le Violon et Cors de Chasse qui peuvent se jouer avec accompagnement de violon et cors de chaffe dediees a Mademoiselle de Moullaine par Mr. Schobert Claveceniste de S. A. S. Monseigneur le Prince de Conty, Op X. Chez M. Bailleux Md. De Musique ordinaire du Royale de la famille Royale et de l'Ecole Royale de Musique [Paris, ca. 1785]. Prix: 4f.
    Six Sonates pour Clavecin Ou Forte Piano avec accompagnement de Violon et Violoncelle composes par Jean Cretien Bach Maitre de Musique de sa Majeste la Reine D'Angletaire, Oeuvre XV. Chez le St. Seiber, musician, rue St. Honore a L'hotel D'Aligre Ancien Grand Conseil ou l'on phisieur nouveaux oeuvre [Paris, ca. 1775-79]. Prix: 9. Four double-sided pages including a Sonata VI and a cello part are tucked into the back cover. These do not appear to be loose pages from this volume.
  - Manuscript and music book bound with string containing several works for solo keyboard., Pages numbered in upper right corner, 1-11, and continues after 11 without pagination. Inscribed: "Virginia J. Randolph." Several different handwritings. (Box-folder 6:27)
    Unidentified piece for solo keyboard. Poem handwritten on right margin and bottom margin: Forget me not when friends and smiling.
    Quick Step from the Battle of Salamonca bottom half of page 2
    Gavot
    Overture to Lodoiska by Knetzer
    Cony Owen bottom half of page 5
    Allemande by Stebelt (?) bottom half of page 8
    The Chace bottom half of page 9
    Dutch Minuet
    The Nightingale bottom of page 10
    The Windsor Forester's March bottom half of page 11
    Murphy Delany by Latowr (?) second line of page
    Jack Lahn
    Additional Variations [6 and 7] to Duncan Grey
    Song by Lord Lytellton, Lord MacDonald's Reel
    New Crazy Jane song with English text: Why fair maid in every feature
    L'air comme un Eclair de la Fausse Magie, Arietta with French
    Air des deux petits L'avoyards (?)
    Rural Felicity with variations
    Menuet
  - Manuscript music book containing pieces for solo keyboard and voice with keyboard accompaniment., Inscribed: "Ellen Wayles Randolph, Eliza Waller, Jane Blair Cary. Virginia." Several different handwritings and many unidentified pieces. (Box-folder 6:28)
    Unidentified programmatic piece for solo keyboard with military descriptions written throughout the score.
    God Save the Commonwealth
    Rise Cynthia Rise
    When Sheep are in the Folds, song with English text
    One Morning Very Early, partial song with English text
    Lullaby, song with English text in two verses
    Sonata of Edelman
    German Waltz (this interrupts the Edelman sonata, which continues on the next page)
    La Canonade by Balbastre
    La Triomphante (cannot make out composer's name)
  - Many loose sheets of fragmentary manuscripts in various handwritings, a few pieces tied together with string, many with titles, some without. (Oversize 6:29)
    Unidentified fragments of music for solo keyboard instrument
    Several vocal exercises
    Charming Village Maid solo melody and texted verses
    The following pieces for solo keyboard instrument:
    Aurora
    Air by Herring
    New York Serenading Waltz
    The following pieces arranged for four instrumental parts:
    Vedrai Carino
    Fin Ch'han del vino[from Don Giovanni by Mozart]
    Batti Batti[from Don Giovanni by Mozart]
    The following pieces arranged for keyboard instrument duet:
    Valse Hongroise
    Air de Ballet
    Rondo de Paganini
    The following songs for voice and keyboard instrument accompaniment, with texted verses:
    There's Nothing True But Heaven
    Ye Lingring Winds
  - Manuscript music book, bound but fragmentary. (Oversize 6:30)
    Vocal scales and exercises
    The Haunted Tower for solo keyboard instrument in variations
    Life Let Us Cherish arranged as keyboard instrument duet
    There's Nae Luck About the House song with keyboard instrument accompaniment and texted verses in variations
    The Knight Errant arranged as a rondo by Holst
    Variations on Sicilian Hymn
    Hungarian Waltz
    A Favorite Scots Air
    Air in The Battle of Marengo
    The Waltz Cotillion
    Fin Ch'han del Vino from Mozart's Don Giovanni
    De Tanti Palpiti
    Merrily Danced the Quaker's Wife
    Air du Barbier de Seville: Je Suis Lindor
    The Spanish Fandango
    Clementi's Grand Waltz
    Overture of Panurge by Gretry
    Overture de Chimene
    Choeur de Voyageurs de la Caravanne
    Air Lison Dormoit
    Home Sweet Home
    Bonaparte's Grand March
    A Much Admired Waltz by Mozart
    God Save the Emperor
    Lord Courtney
    Gramachree with variations
    The following songs with keyboard instrument accompaniment and texted verses:
    The Portrait
    Come Rest in This Bosom
    The Ill Wife
  - New and Complete Preceptor for the Spanish Guitar with Progressive Exercises Selected from the Works of the Best of Authors. Printed method book for Spanish Guitar., Contains 14 pages, some are missing. (Box-folder 6:31)
    Published by John G. Clemm, Philadelphia, 1827, sold at P. Thompson's, Washington. Price: $1. Contains:
    Several pages of instructions and exercises
    Where Roses Wild Were Blowing
    The Gallant Troubadour
    Comin' Thru the Rye
    Draw the Sword Scotland
  - Small, string-bound manuscript music notebook of songs for voice and keyboard accompaniment, with texted verses, in handwritings of Martha Jefferson Randolph and several others. (Box-folder 6:31)
    A Poor Little Gypsy by Arne
    The Silver Moon by Hook
    Owen - a Welch Song
    Ellen Aroon
    Flutt'ring Spread Thy Purple Pinions
    Air du Barbier de Seville
    Life Let Us Cherish
    Song in the Stranger
    Crazy Jane
    When Pensive I thought of My Love from Bluebeard
    The Tear
    Poor Richard
    Ah! Gentle Hope
    The SailorBoy
    The Wedding Day
    Dear Nancy I've Sailed the World All Around
    M'ha Detto la mia mama by Martini
    Thou Art Gone Awa' Mary
    Flora
    A Prey to Tender Anguish
    Psalm 148
    Old 100th Psalm
    Psalm 134
    Psalm 57, verse 8 by Handel
    Psalm 146, verse 6 by Handel
    Psalm 42, verse 9 by Handel
    Easter Hymn
    Sanctus
    Lewis Gordon
    Evening Hymn
    The Mermaids Song by Haydn
    The Blind Boy
    Duke of Yorks March
  - Two pages of manuscript music and notes in the hand of Thomas Jefferson. Opening phrases of compositions of Carlo Antonio Campioni which Jefferson owned., Inscribed: "On this paper is noted the beginning of the several compositions of Campioni which are in possession of T. Jefferson. He would be glad to have everything else he has composed of Solos, Duets, or Trios. Printed copies would be preferred; but if not to be had, he would have them in manuscript." (Box-folder 6:34)
- Part 2: Music from the library of Thomas Jefferson
  A collection of eighteenth-century songs. Inscribed "John Wayles," father-in-law of Thomas Jefferson. This bound volume consists of several books of songs and many loose pieces of sheet music all bound together as one volume. In the last part of the volume, many of the loose pieces of sheet music were mounted on pages from the Bristol Journal.
  Forms part of the Tracy W. McGregor Library A 1723 .J4 no.1-95.
  - Lyric Harmony Consisting of Eighteen entire new Ballads with Colin and Phaebe, in Score. As performed at Vauxhall Gardens by Mrs. Arne and Mr. Lowe Composed by Thomas Augustine Arne, Opera Quarta.
    Songs with vocal parts and keyboard instrument accompaniment, including figured bass, and texted verses. Printed for the author by Wm. Smith Music Printer and seller in Middle Row, Holborn, [ca. 1740-41].
    Contains: The Kind Inconstant, The Invitation, The Charms of Isabel, The Complaint, The Rover Reclaim'd, Philosophy no Remedy for Love, Colin's Invitation, The Generous Distress'd, Kindness and Gracefull Air Preferr'd to Beauty, Cloe Generous as Fair, The Lovesick Invocation, The Fond Appeal, To a Lady, who, Being Asked by her Lover for a Token of Her Constancy, Gave Him a Knife, The Contest Between Love and Glory, The Dumps, The Happy Bride, Colin and Phaebe: A Pastoral.
  - A Second Collection of Favorite Songs Sung at Vauxhall by Mrs. Pinto & Mrs. Weichsell Composed by John Christian Bach.
    Songs with text and accompaniment for 2 violins, flute, horn, and bass. Printed by Welcker in Gerrard Street, St. Ann's, Soho, London [ca. 1762-68]. The songs are only titled by who sung the song. Songs listed by first lines of text:
    In This Shady Blest Retreat...
    Smiling Venus Goddess Dear...
    Tender Virgins Shun Deceivers...
    Lovely Yet Ungrateful Swain...
  - The Laurel Book II A New Collection of English Songs and Cantatas Sung by Mr. Lowe and Miss Falkner at Vaux-hall and Marybon Gardens Composed by Mr. Joseph Baildon.
    Songs with texted verses and accompaniment for either keyboard instrument or small chamber ensemble. Printed for I. Walsh, in Catherine Street in the Strand, London [ca. 1736-66]. Songs listed by first lines of text:
    Should fate in some kind hour decree...
    Believe not youth with wit or sense to gain the heart of woman...
    Haste, Lorenzo, hither fly ... [as Jessica in The Merchant of Venice]
    Gentle Youth, ah! why this pressing
    On pleasure's smooth wings
    In Cupid's famed school
    Bid me to live and I will live thy constant swain to be
    Cantata
    (On separate sheet) The Love Rapture: A New Song Set by Mr. Arne
  - The Jessamine A Collection of Six New Songs, Composed by Mr. Thomas Curtis Organist of St. Mildred's, Bread Street Set for the Violin, German Flute, with a Thorough Bass for the Harpsichord or Organ.
    Printed and sold for the author by I. Cox at Simpson's Musick Shop in Sweeting's Alley, opposite the East Door of the Royal Exchange, London [ca. 1765-96]. Contains:
    The Self Contest
    The Confused Lover
    Aminta's Choice
    Strephon's Invitation
    The Advice
    Then Maidens Like Me Resolve to be Free
    The True Britton
  - The Ballads Sung by Mr. Dibdin this Evening at Ranelagh And a Conclusion Piece Properly transposed for the German Flute and Guittar Composed by Mr. Dibdin.
    Printed for the composer and sold at his house in Chelsea, at the Lyre and Owl, in St. Martin's Lane; at Mr. Griffin's bookseller in Catharine Street & at Ranelagh House, [ca. 1764-76]. Songs listed by first lines of text:
    My Nancy was as neat jade...
    There was a fair maiden, her name it was Gillian...
    A Conclusion Piece, 22 pages with four vocal parts and instrumental accompaniment
  - Three Cantatas Composed by Mr. G. Hayden [Haydn].
    Printed for John Johnson music-seller at Harp and Crown in Cheapside, London [ca. 1740-62].
    Martillo
    Thyrsis
    Neptune and Amymone
  - A Collection of Songs Sung at Marybone Gardens by Mr. Rennoldson Set to Music by Mr. Heron Organist of St. Magnus London Bridge and to the Earl of Peterborough Book IV.
    Songs with texted verses and accompaniment for German Flute, Violin, or harpsichord. Engraved, Printed and Sold by Longman, Lukey and Co. No. 26 Cheapside, London [ca. 1769-75].
    Young Collin
    Dolly's Petition
    Damon and Phyllis
    The Invitation
    The Rose
    The Moth
    Polly
    A Hunting Song
  - A Collection of Songs Sung at Marybone Gardens by Miss Thomas Set to Music by Mr. Heron Organist of St. Magnus London Bridge and to the Earl of Peterborough Book V, 1771.
    Songs with texted verses and accompaniment for German Flute, Violin, or harpsichord. Engraved, printed, and sold by Longman, Lukey & Co. No. 26 Cheapside, London.
    The Cuckoo
    Damon
    Stern Winter
    Rise Glory
    Patie(Scotch Song)
    The Choice
  - The Favorite Songs Sung At Ranelagh for the Voice and Harpsichord Also adapted for the Guitar.
    Published according to Act of Parliament and Entered in Stationer's Hall. Printed for Robert Bremner at the Harp and Hautboy opposite Somerset House in the Strand, London [ca. 1762-89]. Songs listed by first lines of text:
    Come Ye Hours... by Vento
    Not on Beauty's Transient pleasure by Giardini
  - An English Cantata called Sylvia The Morning Fresh and four other English Songs Set to Musick by Michael Christian Festing.
    Original cover page not included in collection, but a photocopy the Library of Congress indicates that the subsequent twelve sheets of music come from the title above. Contains: Recits and arias with the words from Tasso's Aminta and Waller's Poems.
    Phillis and Silvano
    Chloris
  - Songs with texted verses and keyboard instrument with figured bass and/or the German flute and/or guitar accompaniment.